- I'm Brad.
- I'm Mike.
And behind the scenes we have Bob.
And together we're the most famous
physical therapy team on the internet.
- Well, in our opinion, of course, Mike.
- And if you're new to our channel,
make sure to subscribe.
We appreciate all of you
joining our community.
Now, the topic of the day is,
do you wake up having back,
shoulder or neck pain?
'Cause Brad certainly is right now.
- Oh yeah. Well, we're gonna talk,
and actually take a trip down memory lane.
We have a video that
has viewed by millions,
and very appreciative of our tips.
Plus, we're gonna show a couple new tips
at the end of the video to amend it.
- So, go back in time.
- Woo woo woo woo woo.
♪ Bob and Brad ♪
♪ The two most famous ♪
♪ Physical therapists on the internet ♪
It's not that easy.
We just can't say don't
do this and don't do that.
- We gotta give 'em a reason.
- We're here for a little education
so that once you become educated,
you understand, and then you do.
There's a whole philosophy.
- Sure.
- But we don't want to get into that.
But the biggest areas that cause,
that are complaints of pain,
are neck, shoulder, and back.
- And back.
- Right. Those are probably
the most common areas
that become irritated and
painful throughout the night.
So we've gotta take care of this,
and address and understand
it a little bit.
First of all, joints in general,
whether it's your, the
joints in your spine,
or your shoulders, or your back,
or whatever it may be, your neck,
wanna stay in what we call
the "loose pack" position.
- Right. And I like
being at the end range.
- Right. So my shoulder
here would be loose packed.
Up here would be end range.
- Right.
- Okay?
- Or back here would be end range.
- Right.
- So I wouldn't sleep
like this either.
- Right.
So neck, if we put our neck
over to one side this way,
or one side that way,
all the joints in your neck
are pushed to the end range we call it.
And that's uncomfortable
after a period of time.
Initially it may not be a problem,
but, you hold your neck
over like this for,
you know, 20 minutes or more,
it becomes uncomfortable.
So, keeping that in mind,
the next thing we wanna
do is look at the spine.
And not just look at it,
but understand the spine moves,
and it twists and whatnot.
But we wanna keep it in
a neutral position, Bob.
- Correct.
- Okay.
So a neutral position is actually
where there's a little
curve in the back here.
There's a curve in the
other direction in the-
- So we've got a curve
in, curve out, curve in.
- Right.
- Yep.
- Yep. So we want to keep-
- Kinda S shape.
- Yep.
Keep these curves in,
in that kind of a general shape, you know?
- Yeah.
- So we're not going way out.
And if you look at it from the front view,
now that, you typically
want to keep straight.
- Right.
- So the curves
are looking from the side,
and this is looking straight.
So this will all come to play
when we look at our
positioning with sleeping.
So, anything else that I missed?
- No, you got it right, Brad.
- Alright. So-
- For once.
- Let's look at the position...
Yeah, for once.
Well, it happens, I was up
studying late last night.
- Here we go.
- So the first position is
we're gonna talk about prone.
- Okay.
- Laying on your stomach.
- So this is a bad position.
- Right.
This is, this is a position
because it breaks a number of the rules
we just talked about that create pain,
gives you outta that neutral position,
or puts you at end range.
So if I'm gonna lay here,
let's just take a
regular pillow, Bob once.
- Sure.
- And there are people who sleep prone,
and they have for a while,
and they do okay with it.
But the problem that can
really occur when you're,
when you're on your stomach,
you almost have to have
your head one position over,
over to the right or to the left.
And that puts my neck at end range,
and I'm laying there for
a long period of time.
Now, I'm assuming people
who sleep like this,
that don't have pain throughout the night,
turn their head right to left.
- Well, the other thing is though,
and I didn't see a study on this,
but we did do kind of an informal survey
of this at a classroom one time.
We asked how many people have headaches.
- Yep.
- And a hundred percent
of the people that laid on
their stomach had headaches.
- Sure.
- During the, you know,
- Throughout the day?
- Throughout the day
or throughout the week.
You know, I mean, had a
higher incidence of headaches.
- Okay. Sure.
- So that's something
to consider is that if you are
especially having those headaches
that start from back here-
- Yep.
- You know, the neck headaches.
- I would,
that's one of the things
I would definitely look into.
- Sure.
And I think, you know, if you're,
if you are a prone sleeper,
you may or may not have a pillow.
I guess without a pillow,
it puts you more in a neutral position.
But you know, still,
if you can avoid the prone position,
for your neck, it's gonna be better.
And then the other thing,
is if you lay in your stomach
and with your shoulders,
if you lay like this,
that puts your shoulders at end range,
and it also puts your,
your brachial plexus-
- [Bob] Brachial plexus.
- and they can get pinched off,
and actually cut the circulation
off into your arms or pinch the nerves,
and you can wake up with numb or-
- [Bob] I have.
One time I woke up,
both my arms were numb
to the point I couldn't,
and I was trying to turn the alarm off,
so I'm going like this.
(Bob and Brad laugh)
It's just-
- Yeah.
- it's a little embarrassing.
- Right. So, and that's,
you know, there's a name for that, Bob.
- [Bob] What is it?
- When you put your arms up like this.
Working overhead.
- [Bob] Sure. What is it?
- I can't remember.
(Bob and Brad laugh)
- I know there's honeymoon syndrome where,
if your, you know, spouse
falls asleep on your arm,
that becomes numb then.
- Right.
- So.
- So, next position, Bob.
I'll think of that in just a little bit.
- Alright.
- Sideline. Now this is, you might say,
"Well everyone sidelines."
- Right.
- Most people do,
which I do myself.
But, oftentimes a shoulder
problem will happen
when you're laying on the
point of your shoulder
if you will.
And the joint, when you relax,
you can sublux or actually
push the ball, the joint,
shoulder joint out slightly,
and can put pressure on the
ligaments and the capsule,
et cetera in your shoulder and cause pain.
So laying like this on the shoulder
can really create some pain.
So what you'll wanna do
is pull this shoulder out
a little bit so you're actually on
a little bit of a slant here, versus here.
- And you actually, yeah,
then you're getting more on the meaty
part of the shoulder that
can handle it on the back there.
- Yep. And that's gonna help reduce that.
So the sideline can be a problem,
but if you do these little twerks
that we're talking about,
it'll help you out.
- We show way we can do
another thing for that too.
But Brad, the other thing,
while you're in this position,
the other thing is your back
is sagging a little bit.
- Sure. When you're in
this sideline position.
- Yeah. Let's get the
spine out and show that.
- So here, you know, it's straight,
but now it's gonna sag a little bit
right here in the low back.
- Yeah. Right.
- And so if you're having
back problems and if you,
especially you sleep like
this a lot all the time,
you should take like a rolled
towel like we did here,
and you can put it in that position.
Or there's actually a
sleep roll you can buy.
- Yeah.
- We have it
in our Amazon section there by Mackenzie.
And this one you can actually
tie around your waist,
so it's in your back when
you sleep on your back,
or it's on your side when
you sleep on your side.
- Right. Yep.
- So.
- And, and you know, in my case,
I know I can sleep on my
side for about 10 minutes.
I never even get to sleep,
'cause my back starts to hurt,
then I have to go to my my back.
But that's just 'cause
of my spondylothesis.
So this is how this works.
This one's a little bit small for me.
It doesn't wrap around.
But people who have a disc problem,
often they use something like this,
so that here you have the
support on your low back
in the lor, in the lordotic section.
And then when you roll to either side,
you also have that hollow
spot being filled in.
- There's another possibility right here
besides it being too small for you.
Maybe your waist is too big for it.
- Yeah, there you go.
(Brad laughs)
- Just point out that possibility.
- Should we-
- Let me-
- Should we show 'em the
trick with the pillows?
- Yeah, sure. Let's do that.
- Let's pull this right here.
- Yeah.
- So this is a
cervical pillow here.
But another way, I'm gonna
put this on this side Brad,
just for my mic purposes here.
So, you know, generally
when you're on your side,
if you're gonna lay on your side,
you want to have a thicker pillow.
- [Brad] Yep.
- So that your neck
isn't going like...
Why don't you take it out once Brad.
It isn't going like this.
- Right.
- You want to have your neck
right in the middle too.
So this is almost a little bit-
- Yep.
- This one would actually
need to go up a little bit.
- Right. So, but the other key,
we've showed this many times,
is actually you take a pillow,
a lot of times it's
more of a throw pillow,
and that's what I use.
- Sure.
- And I just create the little canal here.
- [Brad] Yep.
- And you can put
your arm right in there.
And now there's not nearly
the pressure on your
shoulder there was before.
- So this is that sideline
making sideline tolerable
and acceptable to keep the
shoulder pain from waking you up.
- And now if you're having
pain in this shoulder,
and you don't wanna lay on it,
which is good, then you should actually,
besides the canal, well you
might not even need the canal.
- Right.
- But you would
put a pillow here, and
another pillow here,
and support the arm like this.
- Right. Right.
- And again, it puts that shoulder
in that loose packed position
that Brad was talking about.
It's not any end range,
and it's kinda a little bit forward.
- Sure.
- And it's not,
it's not going to cross
the body like this.
which is also bad.
- Right. Because then you're getting
towards that end range, and
you know, irritating them.
- Right here in the middle.
That's where you want to keep it at.
It's gonna do it well.
- Right. And the last thing is sideline.
A lot of people will
get a pillow like this
that actually has the form,
and it's a memory foam.
- Right. So get put in and
there's a gap for the neck.
- Right. So you get the
neck in a neutral position.
- Sure.
- And that's not necessary.
You can use a regular pillow.
And some people, you know,
I'll have some people
try just a towel roll
to fill in that gap to get
that neutral position in the neck.
So if I lay here now with the towel roll,
see how it's, it really
cradles my neck nicely.
- Right.
- So, and now we don't
have the neck sagging either.
- Right.
- So,
that's actually pretty comfortable.
- Yeah. If this works, but
it's not quite as cushy,
you may wanna invest in the memory foam.
They cost a little more but-
- Or there's the cervical roll too.
- Oh yeah. The cervical.
- We got all sorts of good-
- Yeah, there's a, there's a lot of things
to keep you comfortable.
- Mackenzie makes a roll here with
cervical where you can put it in there.
- Sure.
- And if you find the towel works well,
and you don't want to
keep using the towel,
you can go and get one of those.
- Right.
- So what it boils down to,
we got two positions to avoid, the prone,
which we don't have any solutions for.
And sideline, which we have
a number of solutions for
that we just went through.
So you know, we're helping you
out at least on half of the-
- We're half smart.
- Right.
Whoa! And the time
machine returns to 2024,
and we have Mike with us today.
These are in for three positions
that weren't mentioned in that film,
and Bob said we've gotta mention
these to make this updated.
Mike, what are the three?
- Well it's only two
positions, but three remedies.
- Oh.
- So first,
two are for stomach sleepers,
and then we got sideline.
So the first one,
if you are a stomach sleeper,
but you are having some
hip or low back pain,
take another pillow,
place it under your waist,
and you're gonna lay on that pillow there.
What does this do, Brad?
- Well it actually flexes
the hip and the low back.
And if you have stenosis
in particular like myself,
this makes a tremendous amount
of different in comfort.
Simply put it there,
adjust it up and down
where it feels comfortable,
and you'll know, 'cause it'll just feel
a night and day difference
if that's what you need.
And what about the neck?
- If you're having some neck
pain in your stomach sleeper,
I typically use two pillows.
I sleep in all positions
'cause I'm a weirdo.
Anyway, you place this here,
you don't want your neck to be cranked
all the way to 90 degrees like this.
I've woken up like this,
and it's very uncomfortable.
So oftentimes if you put another pillow
kind of underneath your chin,
and more at a 45 degree angle,
and I'm half talking in
the pillow right now,
so don't mind me,
it's much more comfortable.
Obviously you can't sleep like that.
So, 45 degree angle if you're
having some neck discomfort
and you're a stomach sleeper.
- Right. We don't say
cranked, we say rotated by.
This is a, this is a family
show, and a therapy show.
- It's a, it's a medical term, "cranked."
- Anyway.
- Anyways.
- Last one, if you're
having some hip pain,
side hip pain and you're a side sleeper,
what you can try to do is place a pillow
underneath your rib cage,
kind of above the hip,
above the hip, A bove.
Anyway. And then you can also
put a pillow underneath your foot.
This is gonna help rotate
your hip in a different way,
taking the pressure off your lateral side.
- That's right. A lot of these will help
get the spine back in the neutral,
whether it's in the low back or the neck,
making it much more comfortable,
so you can sleep and relax to position.
- Now if you watch this whole video,
we would like to know.
Comment down below, your
favorite sleeping position,
because we're very curious, aren't we?
- Right. Or if you've got another hint
that other people will benefit from,
make sure you let us
know about that as well.
So we help each other out.
And we've got another video
that will be helpful as
well with more detail.
- Yeah, so if you're having shoulder pain,
I don't think we addressed it much
in the old video or this one.
You can click the video link on a screen,
"How to stop shoulder pain in bed."
- That's right, and the famous
Bob's Eerie Canal Theory
and Method to eliminate shoulder pain.
And that's what he uses.
So if you wanna find out
what it is, check it out.
It's very, very new.
- No water is involved.
(Brad chuckles)
♪ Bob and Brad ♪
♪ The two most famous ♪
♪ Physical therapists on the internet ♪